[Music]
hello everybody and thank you for tuning
in to the Liberty Report with me today
is Daniel McAdams Daniel good to see you
good morning Dr Paul Daniel we have a
great guest today uh John Karo
and we've talked about him a lot on this
program and he has made an effort to
really reveal the truth to a lot of
people about what's really going on in
particular with the CIA and he has a
book coming out very soon doing time
like a spy what is this doing time that
means our government put him in prison
here he's a truth teller and he ended up
in prison sad story but uh I want to
welcome you to our program John thanks
for being with us thank you so much for
having me I'm thrilled to be here great
I think we'll start off with you telling
the audience a little bit about uh you
know the book coming up uh and why this
might be different than the other two
books that you have written and uh What
uh what it's all about sure I I have
written two other books uh one came out
in 2010 it was a memoir of my years in
the CIA it was called the reluctance spy
my secret life in the cia's war on
terror and then I have a book coming out
in June called The Reluctant Terror I'm
sorry called the uh convenient terrorist
it's it's uh written with Joseph Hickman
a former Guantanamo guard and um we we
hoped that that book would be the
definitive account of the the capture
interrogation torture and Detention of
Abu zubeda who um who I captured in
Pakistan in
2002 uh but this book is different this
is doing time like a spy how the CIA
taught me to survive and thrive in
prison uh I went to prison because I
blew the whistle on the cia's torture
program as you've been so kind to uh to
tell your viewers over the past couple
of years uh I expected to go to a
minimum security Work Camp and indeed
when my when my attorneys asked the
judge to order me to a minimum security
Work Camp she did so with no objection
from the prosecutors now with a Work
Camp there are no bars on the windows
the doors are not locked you can work in
town and you're on your honor to uh to
spend the night in the actual prison
camp building so when I got to prison I
I just literally drove up and and
knocked on the door and and said I'm
John kiraku I'm here to turn myself in
the guard began leading me around to the
back of the actual prison that was
across the street from the camp and I
said no no I'm supposed to be at the
camp across the street and the guard
laughed kind of chortled and said ha not
Accord according to my paperwork you're
not and I told myself all right take it
easy there's nothing you can do don't
complain so five days later I got uh
access to a telephone and I called one
of my attorneys and I said hey they put
me in the actual prison with the
pedophiles and the murderers and the the
drug King Pins what do I do and he said
wow well we could file a motion with a
court but it'll be two years before we
get a hearing and you'll be home by then
he said I'm sorry but you're going to
have to tough it out and I decided on
that day that I was going to use the
skills that the CIA had taught me over
the years to make sure that I remained
safe and remained at the top of the
social Heap in prison and that's exactly
what I did wow wow Amazing Story what
can you give us give us maybe your top
five things that you had to to take out
of your bag of tricks when you realize
you were in a different situation than
you thought you were sure number one is
recruit spies to steal Secrets or
anything else you need and indeed on
your very first day of CIA training this
is exactly what they tell you to do
recruit spies to steal secrets that's
the only way you can get promoted it's
the only way you get ahead in life at
the CIA well in prison it's the same way
um if I need something from let's say uh
the Supply Closet for example High
lighters are banned they're considered
to be Contraband but I know somebody who
sweeps the floor in the uh warden's
office or in the Administrative Office I
work on recruiting that person so he can
steal me uh a highlighter or an eraser
or a pen it sounds so ridiculous now but
it's actually pretty important when
you're in prison um but you get more
than that you establish a relationship
with this person you establish a rapport
and with a rapport comes information and
information is worth its weight in gold
I'll give you another
example uh I had a cousin who came to
visit me and I had been writing a Blog
from prison called letters from Loretto
uh well I knew through the grape vine
that the administration was seeking to
place me in solitary confinement to try
to get me to stop writing these letters
from Loretto in which I was exposing
waste Fraud and Abuse in the prison and
so my cousin came to visit me one day
and when we sat down in the visiting
room he said Hey I just heard an
interesting conversation outside uh one
of the guards asked another guard who's
that guy coming to visit and the the
second guard said kiraku oh the CIA guy
why isn't that guy in solitary and the
guard said I asked the warden that and
the warden said we can't put him in
solitary because he hasn't used any of
our names and I said to my cousin do you
have any idea what important
intelligence that is that means that I
can say anything I want and so long as I
don't use their names they can't do
anything to me and so that's what I did
but there were other rules that I used
like uh one was was used at the CIA kind
of half jokingly it was admit nothing
deny everything make counter accusations
and so uh the the the guards would
harass me and they would call me to the
Lieutenant's office and say things like
why don't you tell me about that fight
in the in the unit last night there was
a fight that broke out and I would say
there was a fight in the unit I had no
idea what do you want me to do your job
for you too now you guys are that bad at
your jobs that you want John kiraka to
do your job for you I said get out of
here leave me alone uh that drove them
crazy but we got ourselves to the point
where they just stopped bothering me
because they knew they were going to get
nothing from me right you know uh John
as I read your resume
you were in the CIA for 15 years and you
describe uh your ideals that prompted
you to get into the uh
CIA uh how did how did that change over
time you had uh uh very good intentions
and uh I I still don't read anything
really nasty about the CIA that you
write but uh what type of transition did
you go through from the time you went in
with these Intentions by the time you
resigned and what prompted the
resignation did it have uh to do with
the case
involved that's a great question I
joined the CIA because public service
was very very important in my family to
hear my grandparents tell the story uh
Franklin Roosevelt was personally
waiting for them at Ellis Island to give
them citizenship and a job right and the
American dream a home and a car and and
thanks to to Franklin Roosevelt in fact
we had a we had a framed photograph of
Franklin Roosevelt on our television
until my grandfather died in
1978 so in our family there was always
this this notion that the country had
been so good to us that we needed to
give something back and when I was in
college I really only considered public
service and for me that public service
was in the CIA I was very very proud of
my CIA service from for most of those 15
years but literally everything changed
on September 11th and all of a sudden I
found myself in an organization that I
just no longer recognized this was an
organization that cared not one wit
about human rights or about civil
liberties and there was no one on
Capitol Hill on the oversight committees
to tell them stop this is wrong and we
need to turn the ship around it just
kept getting worse and worse and worse I
finally left in
2004 um and things continued to worsen I
found myself finally on the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee working for
John krey and thinking that well this is
a foreign affairs oversight committee
I'm going to be able to really have an
impact I can do some hard-hitting
investigations I was the senior
investigator and in fact I wasn't
allowed to do any investigations not
just of Barack Obama's uh state
department but of George W Bush's State
Department as well and I realized then
when I was on Capitol Hill that no one
was serious about oversight that no one
was going to talk about waste fraud
abuse or illegality and um in 2007
finally in an interview with uh ABC News
I decided to very simply tell the truth
and I said in that interview three
things that have completely changed the
course of the rest of my life I said the
CIA was torturing its prisoners I said
that torture was official US government
policy it was not the result of a rogue
officer as President Bush had intimated
and I said that the that the policy had
been personally approved by the
president himself and so what happened
was within a day the FBI started
investigating me and they investigated
me for a year from December 2007 until
December 2008 well they determined in
December 2008 that I had not committed a
crime and they closed the case they
actually sent my attorneys a letter
saying it's called a declination letter
saying they're declining to prosecute me
what I did not know
unfortunately was that four weeks later
when Barack Obama was inaugurated the
most transparent president in history
remember the CIA asked Eric Holder to
secretly reopen the case against me and
so Eric holder's justice department
investigated me for another three years
until January 2012 and then they finally
charged me with five felonies coming out
of that interview including three counts
of Espionage now Espionage is one of the
most grave crimes which with which an
American can be charged and frequently
it carries with it the death penalty if
you can imagine this and this was for
saying that the CIA was torturing its
prisoners and that torture was illegal
not only illegal but it was morally and
ethically wrong and let me add one other
thing uh Dr
Paul one of the great things about
working on the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee is you get to have lunch with
foreign diplomats all the time and just
have really great in-depth conversations
about what's going on in the world and
so I got a call one day from a Japanese
Diplomat uh who invited me to lunch so I
went to lunch and we had a lovely
conversation about Israeli elections and
Turkish elections and whatever the
issues of the day were and at the end of
the conversation he said to me uh so
what's next for you and I said well
actually I think I'm going to resign
soon I promis Senator car that I would
give him two years and it's been two and
a half and I think I'd like to go back
into business for myself very excitedly
he said no no don't do that if you give
me information I can give you money and
I said I said shame on you what's the
matter with you pitching me cold
pitching me like that and I went
directly to the office of the Senate
security officer and I reported that I
had been pitched by a foreign
intelligence officer he called the FBI
the FBI came up and interviewed me and
they asked me to call him back and
invite him to lunch and try to get him
to tell tell me exactly what information
he wanted and how much he was willing to
pay for it so I did that and then I
wrote them a memo and then they asked me
to do it a third time and a fourth time
and a fifth time which I did and finally
he said to me well I've been transferred
to Cairo it's a dream job best of luck I
said okay best of luck and I never saw
him again A year later after my arrest
we received Discovery from the justice
department and in that Discovery we
learned that there never was any
Japanese Diplomat he was an FBI agent
undercover pretending to be a Japanese
Diplomat and trying to get me to commit
real
Espionage and I said to my lead attorney
why would they do such a thing I'm a
patriot and he said they did it because
they had no case and they knew they had
no case and they wanted to get you doing
something that they could legitimately
prosecute you for well now that all this
time has passed and I'm home from prison
now for for just over two years two of
the 12 FBI agents who worked against me
have very discreetly reached out to my
lawyers and they've apologized and
they've said that this was a political
case and that they were ordered to do it
and that they were very sorry that they
hoped that there were no hard feelings
Daniel well that's an incredible story
it's hard to hard to
well you know the you uh no i' I've read
interviews where you've urged other
whistleblowers to go up the chain of
command and not do what you did and I
apparently I mean obviously it's from
the story do do you feel that way what
would you what would you tell someone
now because as you point out well first
of all the media is going to be hostile
often times to
whistleblowers uh the oversight
committees on the Hill are not that much
better if if any better at all what do
you say to a future Ed Snowden who's out
there thinking about exposing uh the
next uh torture thing or something of
that
nature well the very first thing that
person has to do is hire an attorney
who's skilled and experienced in
National Security whistleblowing there
are a half a dozen of them in Washington
hire the attorney first before you say
anything now you can go through this
process in two different ways uh and
first we can look at Tom Drake the NSA
whistleblower Tom Tom did indeed go
through his chain of command he went to
his boss after that he went to the uh
inspector General at NSA then he went to
the general counsel then he went to the
Pentagon Inspector General and then he
went to the house permanent select
committee on intelligence what he ended
up with was nine felony charges
including seven counts of Espionage so
that's what happens when you do it by by
the book you do it the way that you're
trained and supposed to do it um in my
case my chain of command had created the
cia's torture program I knew that I
couldn't go through the chain of command
so um I went to the press and again if
you go to the Press you're going to be
charged under the Espionage Act at least
you were during the Obama Administration
so there's really a situation where
you're damned if you do and you're
damned if you don't there are a lot of
um important media outlets now I say
important because they're widely read
things like the the New York Times The
Washington Post even uh the guardian or
The Intercept that have uh encryption
Keys listed on their websites and so if
you are a national security professional
who wants to report waste fraud abuse or
illegality and you don't want to go
through your chain of command or you
don't want to go publicly to the Press
you can do it by sending the encrypted
information directly to the journalists
uh I fear that that's the only way to do
it otherwise you literally take your
your life into your own hands John I
want to go back to your description
about uh What uh Bush didn't do and what
Obama did and I you're challenging
stereotypes there because most people
would think the Law and Order people are
the Republicans uh our our channel here
sort of takes uh an opinion that uh
they're all the same different blends
Republican Democrats policies end up but
actually you put you put a picture there
that even surprises me to a bit because
uh you know we try to give benefits to
even a Democrat if they're saying the
right thing so this is pretty pretty
amazing that uh uh but believable that
all of a sudden the Democrats are the
ones doing that you weren't even a
republican you know if it was political
or something but uh this this this is
astounding have you thought about that
or thought of uh well this is just an
incident they're all the same or is
there a difference in a much different
way than the general population believes
yeah I I've come to a conclusion I think
about this kind of thing all the time I
I concluded back um even before the 2012
election that there really are very
few major differences between the two
parties the Democrats and the
Republicans they can Tinker around the
edges of issues but neither one of those
parties is really talking about Liberty
about Freedom about civil rights and
civil liberties and human rights and so
I decided before the
2 um well before the 2012 election that
um I was throwing my lot in with the
libertarian party and I understand that
it's a small party I understand that it
only gets a handful of percentage points
in the national elections but you know I
I've come to the conclusion that that a
vote for the lesser of two evils is
still evil and and you have to vote for
for the people who you truly believe
mean the best for the country and to me
those were obviously the
Libertarians uh I I was struck as you
say Dr Paul at at the nixonian obsession
with National Security uh leaks under
the Obama Administration you we talk a
lot about the Espionage Act the
Espionage Act was written in 1917 to
combat German sabator during the first
world war and indeed it was never
updated never it doesn't even mention
the term classified information because
the classification system wasn't even
invented until the mid 19 1950s now
between 1917 and 2009 three
Americans were prosecuted for um passing
classified information to or they call
it National Defense information to to
journalists just in the eight years of
the Obama Administration he prosecuted
eight National Security Professionals
almost three times all preious
presidents combined well to me that's
not the most transparent president in
history his that's a president who's
Waging War on transparency that's a
president who is Waging War on Truth
tellers and on National Security
whistleblowers and that's the kind of
president that you have to stand up and
fight um John I want to get your your
take on Wikileaks you know uh Mike Pomo
the CIA director uh said this past week
he considers Wikileaks a quote a hostile
intelligence service he said Julie nange
is a narcissist who has created nothing
of value value it strikes me that he
wasn't just being hyperbolic it seems to
me as if classifying classifying him
even in a speech to csis as he did as a
hostile intelligence Service uh has a
lot of implications as to how you would
fight it as opposed to declaring it a a
a publisher which is what Wikileaks
tries to or or believes that it is what
is your take on Wikileaks and and and
pmo's recent comments on
it I think you make a very important
Point here um think there really was an
underlying message coming from director
Pompeo and the message is that Wikileaks
will be treated here in the US in the
court system as a hostile uh
intelligence organization and I think
that what that speech was was director
Pompeo laying the groundwork for a a
probable Espionage Act case against
Julian Assange likely in the eastern
district of Virginia where I was
prosecuted where Jeffrey Sterling was
prose uted where charges have been filed
against Ed Snowden the eastern district
of Virginia in Alexandria Virginia is
known as the Espionage court and it's
it's called that because no National
Security defendant has ever won a case
there um the judges are hanging judges
uh the government knows that not only
will it win but if a defendant elects to
go to trial the jury will likely be made
up of people from the district from the
CIA the FBI the Pentagon the the in Ence
contractors the Department of Homeland
Security so if you're charged with a
national security crime in the eastern
district of Virginia you don't have a
prayer and I think that that's what
director Pompeo is preparing the
American public for now is Julia nange a
narcissist sure he is I don't personally
like Julian Assange but with that said
Julian Assange is actually doing a
public service and he is exposing waste
fraud abuse or illegality or threats to
the public health or public safety which
is the legal definition of
whistleblowing I think that this is
going to get much uglier before it gets
any better and I think that it will play
itself out in the eastern district of
Virginia John uh we're gonna have to go
in a little bit but I do want to ask
another question I think we could uh do
this for a long time I I hope we can get
you to come to one of our conferences
someday because you'd be fantastic count
me in I would love what great uh I do
have uh one one one question I want to
follow up on I imagine and you said you
do go out and you do speeches you go to
the college campuses I assume talk to
some young people what do you sense
because when I go to the campuses I
think I end up with a select group and
they're very sympathetic but and you if
if you've talked to some young people in
general are they open to your views or
have you been demonstrated against uh by
you know the extremists on the other
side what kind of receptions have you
received yeah I I'm I'm going to use my
most recent speech as as an example
because this was typical of the way
things have gone for me I spoke two
weeks ago at Youngstown State University
in Youngstown Ohio and the University
was actually very worried about my
speech I actually had to send them three
references before they allowed me on to
campus and the references went to the
chief of the campus police department
which I I actually said to my host it's
a little fascist no that I have to get
the cops permission to speak to a
university but anyway I said fine I'll
fill out your forms you can call my I
referred them to a federal judge who's a
friend of mine the director of security
at the Commerce department and um and a
former Ambassador so they they all
vouched for me but anyway I the keynote
address was was in a church off campus
because they decided on campus that I
was too controversial they expected 50
people I had 125 that showed up and and
these students Dr Paul could not have
been any more
respectful attentive they asked smart
questions I I will acknowledge that I
shocked a lot of them they didn't expect
to hear the story that I told but um but
they were all ears and standing ovation
at the end I sold a bunch of books I've
I've received letters and and emails in
the interim so that's really been
typical of of my um college and
university speeches people really do
want to hear the story
they have open minds and uh and they're
willing to come around to to our line of
thinking well I think we're going to
finish up on that very positive note
because I I think there's a lot of
people out there looking for the truth
and I think that's very important I want
to congratulate you on your activities
and what you're doing especially on your
book coming up doing time like a spy
hope everybody buys that book but thank
you very much for being with us
today thank you so much for having me it
was it was just a great pleasure great
and I want to thank our audience for T
tuning in today and uh I I think it's a
powerful message here on what's
happening to our country what's going on
with our civil liberties what the
challenge really is but also it's an
issue not by political partisanship and
a few different people in Washington
this is a philosophic issue about what
the role of government ought to be it
should be there to protect us protect
our liberties and not trying to run the
world and police our own people I keep
think thinking of the term uh truth is
treason in an Empire of lies and we live
in an Empire now for political
International reasons and personal
Liberties being challenged and uh if you
challenge it it's treasonous just look
at what John has gone through in America
by telling the truth I mean that is such
abuse that's a powerful message and we
in this channel intend to continue with
this message loud and clear and I want
to thank you the audience for the
support you have given our viewership is
growing by Leaps and Bounds I hope you
can help us continue to do this to gain
credibility and thank you very much for
being with us today to come back soon to
the Liberty
[Music]
report for